Pierre Eugène du Simitière collection LCP.DuSimitiere
Library Company of Philadelphia
Pierre Eugène du Simitière collection
1492-1784
LCP.DuSimitiere
Library Company of Philadelphia
3.8 Linear feet
Pierre Eugène Du Simitière (1737-1784) was a collector, artist, and historian, who opened the first public museum, the American Museum, in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. At the American Musuem, Du Simitière presented his many materials collected during his travels and from his collections. The Library Company of Philadelphia purchased many of the manuscript materials at an auction in 1785 following Du Simitière’s death and the closing of the American Museum. The following collection is Du Simitière’s manuscript collection purchased at this auction. The collection reflects his interests and his lifestyle and includes poetry, sketches, watercolors, newspaper excerpts and clippings, treatise, correspondence, lists of nature, historical chronologies, bibliographies, and copies and originals of historical documents. The collection includes compiled information on places such as the West Indies, Pennsylvania, New England, New York, and the Carolinas in the form of historical chronologies, documents, bibliographies, sketches, and narratives. It includes information, documents, and research on many Native American groups and Creoles. The collection also contains information, documents, and research on historical events in the United States such as the Jacob Leisler case, politics in New York, the American Revolution, the colonization of America, and the Pennsylvania Line Mutiny. With the exception of a few miscellaneous items, the collection’s focus is on the years 1720 to 1780.
12 containers, 4 volumes
Du Simitière, Pierre Eugène, ca. 1736-1784
Biographical/Historical note
Pierre Eugène Du Simitière, collector, artist, and historian, was born in Geneva, Switzerland on September 18, 1737 to Jean-Henri and Judith-Ulrique Cunegonde Delorme Ducimitiere. “Du Simitière was a restless man, forever traveling, forever collecting, forever projecting grand schemes in solitude,” (Library Company of Philadelphia, Introduction).
In 1757, Du Simitière sailed from the port of Amsterdam and arrived on St. Eustasius, a Dutch island. It was during this trip that his collecting began. According to the Library Company of Philadelphia, Du Simitière’s collecting, the main purpose of his travels, “cast a very wide net: books, newspapers, manuscripts, broadsides, prints, fossils, coins, medals, Indian artifacts, rocks, plants, and some animals—mostly dried insects and reptiles preserved in alcohol.” Paul Sifton’s research indicates that Du Simitière may have served in the military and that he probably had some training in art prior to his travels. He sketched specimens and scenery during his travels. He became a naturalized citizen of New York in 1769 and settled in Philadelphia in 1774.
Early in his collecting career, Du Simitière gathered materials regarding the natural and civil history of the West Indies and North America, however, after approximately 1770, he appears to have narrowed his focus to North America’s political history. Indeed, his collection particularly focuses on “relations with the Indians in the settlement of the West; and popular, democratic uprisings, including the Leisler Rebellion in New York in 1688, the Zenger freedom of the press trial, the Paxton Rebellion, the Stamp Act crisis, and finally the American Revolution,” (Library Company of Philadelphia, introduction). His attention to collecting ephemeral documents during the American Revolution was extraordinary and he “gathered every pamphlet, broadside, and newspaper he could get his hand on which related to the conflict,” (Library Company of Philadelphia, introduction).
Du Simitière attempted to publish “Memoirs and Observations on the Origin and Present State of North America,” which was based upon his gathered material, however, the United States Congress did not provide either approval or financial support. According to the Library Company of Philadelphia, this “rejection was … a psychological and financial blow from which Du Simitière never recovered.” Painting, instead of serving as a hobby, became his means for supporting himself and he submitted designs for seals for the United States, New Jersey, Delaware, and two other states; painted miniatures; taught drawing; painted portraits; and served as a translator for Congress as he spoke fluent English and several other languages.
Opening the first public museum in Philadelphia, Du Simitière presented his collected gatherings in the form of the American Museum in May 1782 at his home near Arch and Forth Streets. Unfortunately, the cost of upkeep exceeded the proceeds from tickets costing fifty cents. Du Simitiere died in October 1784 at the age of 47. Following his death, the contents of the American Museum were auctioned and the Library Company of Philadelphia purchased the bulk of the manuscript materials in 1785 for 104 pounds.
Du Simitière was “respected and occasionally even honored (Member and Curator of the American Philosophical Society, an honorary Master of Arts from Princeton), but he was never really embraced by his adopted country,” (Library Company of Philadelphia, introduction).
Bibliography:
Library Company of Philadelphia. Pierre Eugène Du Simitière: His American Museum 200 Years After, 1985.
Sifton, Paul Ginsburg. Pierre Eugène Du Simitière (1737-1784): Collector in Revolutionary America. University of Pennsylvania, Ph.D., 1960.
Scope and Contents note
The Library Company of Philadelphia purchased this collection of Pierre Eugene Du Simitière’s manuscripts at the auction of Du Simitière’s American Museum after his death on March 10, 1785. The books and pamphlets bought at the same auction have been dispersed through the Library Company's collections. Du Simitière gathered or copied these manuscripts during his travels in the West Indies, Boston, New York, and while he lived in Philadelphia, where he was a member of and one of the curators of the American Philosophical Society. After the Library Company of Philadelphia purchased the manuscripts, they were bound together. The Historical Records Survey of the Works Progress Administration described the manuscripts in "Descriptive Catalogue of the Du Simitière Papers in the Library Company of Philadelphia" (1940), from which many of the following series and records descriptions have been abstracted. Since the Historical Records survey, many of the bound volumes have been unbound and foldered by the Library Company of Philadelphia. The unbound volumes in the series descriptions contain folder level description; however, the bound volumes are described only as an overall work. For more detail on the bound volumes, see the "Descriptive Catalogue of the Du Simitière Papers in the Library Company of Philadelphia" (1940). Researchers should be aware that the series titles are drawn from the title of the bound volume. It is important to read the entire scope note for each series, because the volumes often contained additional topics than are listed in the title.
The collection includes information on places such as the West Indies, Pennsylvania, New England, New York, and the Carolinas. It includes information, documents, and research on many Native American groups and Creoles. The collection also contains information, documents, and research on historical events in the United States such as the Jacob Leisler case, politics in New York, the American Revolution, the colonization of America, and the Pennsylvania Line Mutiny. With the exception of a few miscellaneous items, the collections focus is on the years 1720 to 1780.
This collection is divided into thirteen series that were established when the manuscripts were in bound volumes. The titles of the series are also developed from the original titles of the bound volumes. The series are titled: “Papers Relating to Natural History,” “Papers Relating to New York,” “Papers relating to Pennsylvania, the Carolinas, etc.,” “Indian Treaties, 1721-1756,” “Original Letters, 1560-1781,” “Papers Relating to the West Indies,” “Original Journals and Extracts,” “Papers Relating to New England and New York,” “Papers Relating to Pennsylvania, New England, Etc.,” “Miscellaneous Papers from Du Simitière (Scraps),” “Papers Relating to New York politics, 1768-1771,” "Prints and artwork, 1758-1790," and "Volume boards, undated." The series are arranged and described in this order.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research use, on deposit at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA 19107. For access, please contact the Historical Society at 215-732-6200 or visit http://www.hsp.org.
Related Archival Materials note
Microfilmed copy of this collection is available at the Smithsonian Archives of American Art.
Additional information regarding is available at New York University.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased by the Library Company of Philadelphia, 1785.
Separated Materials note
The last series in this collection, "Prints and artwork," is stored in the Print Department of the Library Company of Philadelphia.
Leisler, Jacob, d. 1691; Maylem, John, 1739-1762?; Clippings; Correspondence; Indians of North America; Minutes; Native Americans; Natural history; New England--History; New York (State)--History; Pennsylvania--History; Poets, American; United States--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States--History--French and Indian War, 1755-1763; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; West Indies--History
- Series I. Papers relating to Natural History, circa 1763-1773; [963] (Volume 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  The series “Papers relating to Natural History” consists of a bound volume that is composed of thirty-four hand copied manuscripts pertaining to the natural history of North and South America, with a concentration on the West Indies and Santo Domingo, probably dating from 1763 to 1773. Many of the thirty-four manuscripts in the volume are word for word copies of information Du Simitière extracted from books and articles. Du Simitière cites these original works in his manuscripts. The other manuscripts are Du Simitière’s own observations from his travels. The manuscripts include descriptions of various plants and animals, instructions, lists of various forms of life, bibliographies, catalogues, and some papers on archaeological specimens in North and South America. Some topics of the manuscripts include taxidermy, instructions for making cement for the preservation of plants and animals, instructions on making pictures of birds with their feathers, and how to catch and preserve insects and animals.
  The language of the records is mostly French and English, but the volume also contains a small amount of Latin and Creole.
- Series II. Papers relating to New York, 1644-1770; [964]
  The series “Papers relating to New York” documents colonial New York, Dutch colonists in New York, and New York’s position as a British crown territory. Forty-eight of the documents pertain to the case of Jacob Leisler, a militia leader who led an uprising in the lower part of colonial New York in the years 1689 to 1691 against the policies of King James. Other documents include the original petition from the Foot Company, a vow of allegiance to King William and Queen Mary from Captain Charles Lodick and Isaac Lee in 1669, a list of coach owners in New York in 1770, documents relating to New Netherlands’s history from 1644 to 1664, and New York-related watercolors and illustrations done by Du Simitière.
  The material is either hand copies of original documents or documents written by Du Simitière. The date of the copies is unknown, however the original documents were created from 1644 to 1770. The current order of the documents is presumably the order in which the documents were previously bound. Documents appear to be arranged by topic. This series includes correspondence, affidavits, petitions, and depositions. The language of this series is mostly English and Dutch.
  - Complaints of the Dutch West India Company to its government, 1664 February (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Extract from Beschrijvinghe Van Virginia, 1651 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Extract from Beschrijvinghe Van Virginia, Nieuw-Nederlande, Nieuw-Nederlande, Nieuw Engelandt, en d'Eylanden Bermudes, Berbados, en S Christoffel., 1658 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Conditions stipulated in the agreement between the burgomasters of Amsterdam and the Dutch West India Company, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Extracts from David Pietersz De Vries' Voyages, 1655 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Jacob Leisler case and depositions, 1689 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Letter from Colonel Nicholas Bayard to Captain Abram De Payster and Captain John De Bruyn, 1689 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Letter from King William to Captain Francis Nicholson, Lieutenant Governor of New York, 1689 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Jacob Leigler case depositions, 1690 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  - Jacob Leisler order given to Lieutenant William Churcher and his company, 1689 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Petition of Colonel Nicholas Bayard to Jacob Leisler, 1690 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Second petition of Colonel Nicholas Bayard asking pardon of Jacob Leisler and Council, 1690 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - Document in which Jacob Leisler names Abraham Brashor Sheriff of the city and county of New York, 1691 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - Military orders for Albany signed by Jacob Leisler, 1690 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - Commission of Richard Ingoldosby, 1690 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - Letters from Richard Ingoldosby to Captain Samuel Moore, 1690 January 230 (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
  - Proclamation of Jacob Leisler to Major Erardus Bookman, et al., 1691 (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
  - Outline of documents relating to the Jacob Leisler case, 1691 January-March (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
  - Order to arrest Jacob Leisler, 1691 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
  - Memorandum of Jacob Leisler's plea, circa 1691 (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
  - Anonymous account of the trial, circa 1691 (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
  - Jacob Leisler case depositions, circa 1691 (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
  - Document "exposing' the case to the House of Commons, according to Du Simitire, circa 1769 (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
  - Petition of Jacob Leisler's son to King William, 1691 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
  - Petition presented by Jacob Leisler's son to the Lords of the Committee for Trade and Foreign Plantations, circa 1691 (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
  - Order of discharge and petition for others imprisoned with Jacob Leisler, 1692 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 26-34)
  - Three documents relating to the Jacob Leisler case, 1693-1694 (Box 1, Folder 26-34)
  - Petitions relating to the Jacob Leisler case, circa 1691 (Box 1, Folder 26-34)
  - Depositions from the Jacob Leisler case, circa 1694 (Box 1, Folder 26-34)
  - Information taken by Parliamentary Committee regarding the Jacob Leisler case, 1695 April 24-29 (Box 1, Folder 26-34)
  - Answer to objections to Jacob Leisler's bill of attainder, circa 1691 (Box 1, Folder 26-34)
  - Act for reversing the attainder of Jacob Leisler, 1696 (Box 1, Folder 26-34)
  - Letters sent by Mather Plowman to Halifax, Lord President of His Majesty's Privy Council at Whitehall, 1689 (Box 1, Folder 35-37)
  - Letters of Captain Leisler to William III, 1689 (Box 1, Folder 35-37)
  - List of papers sent to England relating to Leisler revolt, 1689 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 35-37)
  - Order to seize fort in New York for William and Mary, 1689 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 38-41)
  - Copy of the dying words of Jacob Leisler and son-in-law Jacob Milborne, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 38-41)
  - A Letter from a Gentleman of the City of New-York to Another, Concerning the Troubles which happen'd in That Province in the Time of the late Happy Revolution, 1698 (Box 1, Folder 38-41)
  - Certificate of reburial of Jacob Leisler and Milborne, 1698 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 38-41)
  - Account of the Jacob Leisler revolt to the people of Amsterdam, 1698 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
  - Bill imposing fine for the use of the term "Leislorito", 1698 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
  - Petition to Richard Earl of Bellemont, Governor of New York, undated (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
  - Deposition of Abraham Gouverneur, 1699 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 45-52)
  - Forty-eight petitions relating to Leisler's case, circa 1700 (Box 1, Folder 45-52)
  - Abstract of an Act to levy taxes to pay expenses of Province New York, undated (Box 1, Folder 45-52)
  - Statement from Captain J. Mauritz to the Commission, 1689, 1701 (Box 1, Folder 45-52)
  - Affidavit of Jacob Mauritz, 1694 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 45-52)
  - Petition of Jacob Leisler regarding award payment, 1712 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 45-52)
  - Patent for land from Edmund Andros, 1768 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 45-52)
  - Map of New York, 1731 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "View of the City of New York as it was in the year 1673", 1769 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - "Plan of the City of New York as it was about the year 1731", undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - "Plan of the City of New York as it was about the year 1731", undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Plan of the City of Albany[?], undated (Box 1, Folder 57-61)
  - View of the City of Albany, circa 1767 (Box 1, Folder 57-61)
  - Drawings of seals, undated (Box 1, Folder 57-61)
  - Article on Evert Duyckinck by Martin Preyser, 1659 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 57-61)
  - Sketch of New York City Hall, undated (Box 1, Folder 57-61)
  - Original petition pledging obedience to King William and Queen Mary signed by Captain Charles Lodwick and other soldiers, 1669 July (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Minutes of the Colonel Sloughter's council relating to Jacob Leisler case, circa 1690 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Outline plan for a treatise on the lands formerly held by the Dutch Division of the county, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - American chronology of historical events with bibliographical reference, undated (Box 1, Folder 65-67)
  - List of families of Dutch extraction remaining in New York in 1769 (Box 1, Folder 65-67)
  - List of coach owners in New York and Boston, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 65-67)
  - Title page of van der Donck's Beschrijvinge Van Nieuw-Nederlandt, 1656 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Itemized list of original papers relating to public transactions in New York, 1689-1714 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - List of families that owned coaches, chariots, and phaetons in New York, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Series III. Papers relating to Pennsylvania, the Carolinas, etc., 1753-1778; [965] (Box 2)
  The series “Papers relating to Pennsylvania, the Carolinas, etc.,” contains thirty-eight manuscripts relating to a miscellany of topics including research and information on Native Americans, natural history, and descriptions and journals of travels. Despite the title, derived from the original volume title, the documents in this series contain information on Pennsylvania and the Carolinas, but they also contain information about Ohio, Massachusetts, New York, New Jersey, and other provinces. Travel accounts include a copy of Lewis Evans’ letter to Richard Peters about Pennsylvania and a copy from George Croghan’s original journal documenting his travels to Ohio in 1748. The documents relating to the Native Americans include list of treaties and conferences between colonists and Native American tribes or the Six Nations; descriptions of Native American culture; and information on Native American languages. This series also includes Du Simitière’s and others’ meteorological journals, numerous extracts and accounts of the discovery of fossils, and drawings of buildings in Rhode Island and Philadelphia.
  Many documents, spanning the years 1738 to 1770, were hand copied by Du Simitière from approximately 1753 to 1778. The current order of the documents is presumably the order in which the documents were previously bound. Documents appear to be arranged by topic. The language of the material is mostly French, Dutch, and English, although there are also some documents in Latin.
  - Indian nations in New England and adjacent countries, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - New England treaties with Indian nations, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ancient Indian nations in the provinces of New York, New Jersey, and Delaware, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Indian names of noted persons, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Indian items, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Indian nations on the East side of North America, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Indian tribes of North America, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hudson Bay Indians, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Indians trading with the French at the time of de la Potherie, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Narrative of a strange old woman with a pair of horns, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - List of North American Quadrupeds, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Land grant from Francis Lovelace to Swen Gonderson, et al., 1741, 1769 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "The Life and Character of a Strange He Monster", 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Account of the Funeral of Andrew Hamilton copied from the Pennsylvania Gazette, 1741 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Elaboration on "The Life and Character of a Strange He-Monster", 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - "Labour in Vain or an Attempt to wash Black Moore white, humbly inscribed to the author of the Chronicle", 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Resolutions of a mass meeting of Freeholders and Freemen of Philadelphia (copy), 1774 June-July (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Cariolanua to Charles Jenkins, 1775 October 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Meteorological journal kept in Philadelphia, Boston, Newport, New York, and Burlington, New Jersey, 1766-1778 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chronological chart of North America, 1512-1656, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Chart of Dutch, English, Swedish, and Indian names of colonial towns and places, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Brief account of Pennsylvania by Lewis Evans (copy), 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Statement of John Patten (copy), 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - George Croghan's journey to the Ohio, 1748-1751 (copy), 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Dunkers. Extract from the Monthly Review of February 1778 regarding letters from the Reverend Jacob Duché to George Washington, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Carolina. Extract from John Lawson's A New Voyage to Carolina, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - A catalog of Carolina birds described by Mr. Robert Stevens, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Short Account of South Carolina, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Plan of Charles-town, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Plan of Boston, 1729, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sketch of the Harbour of Charles Town, South Carolina, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Treaty of Peace between William Bull and Chief Attakulla Kulla, et al., 1761 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Discovery of Florida by Ponce de Leon, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper clippings from the South Carolina Gazette, 1706 (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
  - Materials for a history of South Carolina, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
  - List of books and pamphlets on South Carolina, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
  - Account written by William Hunter in Philosophical Transactions about fossils being found that belong to an elephant, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 29a)
  - Extract from William Robertson's The History of America about animal bones, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 29b-30)
  - Extract from M. Bossu's Travels through Louisiana about finding elephant skeletons, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 29b-30)
  - Rough draft of a memorandum given to Lieutenant Robert Douglass, 1753-1778 (Box 2, Folder 29b-30)